[MUSIC]
I'm Chris Brooks, I'm a research assistant
professor at the School of Information.
I'm director of learning analytics and
research at the office
of academic innovation.
I'm a computer scientist who studies
e-learning, student achievements,
student success, both at higher and
online in situations like in MOOCs.
One thing I remember as a child
my father was a physicist and so
I would go to the university as many
kids do and my kids do now, come and
experience the university and
what it has to offer.
And as a physicist he had
access to some of the first
instances of the worldwide web.
And so I got to sit there and
play with things like NCSA Mosaic Early
versions of Netscape, etc.
and I think it's that connectivity,
the idea that information was now a first
class citizen in the world of sciences.
And so this new world that we're
starting to see with data science,
these are competencies that
learners are learning in preschool.
That are starting to think about data as a
different way of investigating the world.
And I think that for me that started
in a very early stage when I was young
at the university seeing
what my father was doing and
being able to play with computers.
I'm happy to try and bring that
to as many people as possible and
that's really one of the goals of this
Introduction to Data Science with Python.
[MUSIC]