With the Matplotlib magic
having set the back end for us,
we're going to start
our plotting journey by making
a graph using the plot function.
A plot has two axes,
an x-axis along the horizon,
and a y-axis which
runs vertically.
First, let's input the pyplot
scripting layer as PLT.
All of the functions
which will run against
the Pyplot module are part of
the scripting layer
of the architecture.
Let's take a look at
the plot function
by looking at the docstring.
If you're not used to seeing it,
this Python function declaration
with two arguments,
the star args, and
the double star kwargs
can be a bit obscure.
What's being said here by
the star args is that
the function supports any number
of unnamed arguments.
The double star keyword args also
means that it supports
any number of named arguments.
This makes the function
declaration very flexible since
you can pass in basically
any number of arguments,
named or not,
but it makes it
difficult to know what
is an appropriate argument.
Reading on, we see that
the arguments will be
interpreted as x, y pairs.
So let's try with just one
data point at position 3,2.
Here, we see that
the return value
is aligned to the object,
and we see our first
figure up here.
We don't see the data points
though, which is a bit odd.
It turns out that the third
argument should be a string which
signifies how we want
that data point to be rendered.
Let's use a period for a dot,
and we'll see that our data
point shows up, there we go.
You'll notice that the
subsequent calls to plot
have actually updated
our visualization.
This is a particular feature
of this interactive backend,
other backends might not.
For instance, you might see
some web tutorials using
the older %matplotlib
inline magic
instead of the %matplotlib
notebook magic.
The inline magic is
not interactive,
so subsequent calls create
new plots as new cells
in the notebook,
and this can be handy too.
Here's where some of
the confusion with
matplotlib as a library
tends to come from.
In the last lecture, I
explained that there's
an Artist layer,
and that it is figures with
subplots and axes
and data points,
which are rendered as
patches onto these axes,
but we haven't seen
any of that here.
Instead, we just
called one function on
a module named plot,
so what's going on?
The pyplot scripting interface
is managing a lot
of objects for you.
It keeps track of
the latest figure of subplots,
and of the axis objects.
Moreover, it actually hides
some of these behind
methods of its own.
So the pyplot module itself
has a function which
is called plot,
but it redirects calls to
this function to the
current axes object.
This makes for a
significant learning curve,
and you'll see many discussions
in web tutorials,
and Stack Overflow, where
people are confused
by these two different approaches
to making figures show up.
So let's take a look at
a comparable approach
that's a bit more verbose,
and some people would call this
the matplotlib object API,
but I think it's more
accurate to think of it as
directly interfacing with
the Artist layer instead.
First, I'm going to import
a new backend called
FigureCanvasAgg.
I don't have to use
the module-level use function
since we're not calling this
from the scripting API.
Also import the figure object.
Then we'll go ahead and create
a new figure and associate
it with the backend.
We can then add a subplot
directly to this.
We're going to talk more about
subplots in a future lecture,
but this number 111
actually means that we
just want one plot.
The return value for
the subplot is the axes object,
which contains
methods for plotting,
so we can plot
our image as per usual.
Now, the backend
that we're using,
the one for the Jupyter Notebooks,
isn't able to render
this directly,
since it expects
the scripting layer,
pyplot, to have created
all of the objects.
So here we'll save the figure
to a png file instead.
Then, we'll do
a quick HTML cell magic,
and execute that and
see the rendered image.
That's a lot more work than
using the scripting layer.
The scripting layer
though isn't magic,
it's just doing some of the
behind the scenes work for us.
For instance, when
we make a call
to pyplots plt.plot,
the scripting layer
actually looks to
see if there's a figure
that currently exists,
and if not, it creates a new one.
It then returns the
axes for this figure.
We can actually get
access to the figure
using the GCF function,
which stands for get
current figure of pyplot,
and get access to the
axes as well using
the GCA function,
get current axes.
okay. Let's create
a new figure with pyplot.
This means it won't update
our figure at the top
of this file.
Then, let's make a plot,
grab the axes, and set
the x and y limits.
We can do this using
the axis function.
This function takes
four parameters:
a minimum value for x
which we'll put it zero,
a maximum value for x which
we'll put at six. Then,
corresponding minimum
and maximum values
for y which we'll
put at zero and 10.
Since we're doing this
with the scripting layer,
once we run the Jupyter cell,
it renders to the nbagg backend
as we might expect.
All right, one more demonstration
on the fundamentals of
putting together a plot.
You can add Artists to an
axes object at any time.
Pyplot is doing this for
us when we call
the plot function.
It's determining what shape
we want from the string,
the location associated
with that shape,
that it's creating
a patch object,
and adding that to the axes.
If we make subsequent calls
to the plot function,
this will add more data
to our chart.
You can see that
when this is done,
the points are rendered
in different colors as
the axes recognizes them
as different data series.
But we can go further with
the axes object to
the point where we can
actually get all of the child
objects that that axes contains.
We do this with the axes
get_children function.
Here, we can see that
there's actually
three line to the objects
contained in this axes,
these are our data points.
A number of spines which are
actual renderings of the borders
of the frame including
tic markers,
two axis objects, and a bunch
of text which are
the labels for the chart.
There's even a rectangle
which is the background
for the axes.
Okay, so there's
a whirlwind tour of
how to be productive
with matplotlib
and make your first chart.
In the next lecture,
we're going to go
through some of the
different built-in
charting options
which are available to us.