Interactivity and
animation are very similar in Matplotlib.
For interactivity though, we have to head
down to the artist layer a bit more.
In particular, we have to reference
the canvas object of the current figure.
The canvas object handles all
of the drawing events and
it's tightly connected
with a given back end.
If event listening is something
you're not familiar with,
it can be a bit of
a tough concept to grasp.
For decades,
computers have had abstract methods for
doing multiple things at once and now with
multiprocessing and multi-core machines,
there's actually physical ways
Is to do many thing at once.
But even before that,
the abstraction news was largely
focused on the notion of events.
Moving a mouse pointer for instance would
create an event, clicking will create
an event, pressing on keys on
the keyboard would create an event.
And this didn't only happen at the
hardware level such as IRQ interrupts but
at the software level as well.
In fact, event driven programming has
infiltrated most of the ways computer
programmers regularly
engage with software.
From HTML and JavaScript,
down to lower level C code.
You can think of an event as a piece
of data which is associated with
a function call.
And when the event happens, the software
environment, in our case this is
Matplotlibs backend, will call
the function with the relevant data.
Let's look at a trivial example.
We'll create a new figure and
plot some random data to it.
Then we'll create a new
function called onclick.
And this takes one parameter,
which is the event object.
So what's in an event object?
Well, that depends on
the type of the event.
Here we're going to
deal with mouse events.
And they have both an x and
a y value as far as the location of
the mouse in pixels on the canvas.
As well as an x and
a y values first location of the mouse
relative to our data and axis.
So for our onclick we'll clear
the current axis then plot our data
then set the title of the plot to
be variance location of the mouse.
Finally, we have to connect this
events to an event listener and
this process is usually
called wiring it up.
In this case very easy,
get the current figure and
its canvas subject then call
the mpl_connect function.
Passing in the string for
button_press_event as well as
reference to the function onclick, which
will be call when the event is detected.
Now when we click on our plot we see
the most information printed to the title.
The Matplotlib documentation describes
the kinds of events you can listen from.
But whether they work or not,
depends on the backend you're using, and
some backends are not interactive.
Button presses, key presses,
scroll events and figuring axis enter and
leave events are almost common.
But the most important event for
us is the pick event.
The pick event allows you
to respond when the user is
actually clicked on a visual
element in the figure.
Let's look at an example.
For this, I want to create a list
of countries in randomized order.
We can do this with the shuffle
function from the random module.
Then I'll create a new DataFrame with
random values for height and weight, and
another column for origin.
Great, now we have some
C data to play with.
Now we can create a scatterplot with
the x and y values as the height and
weight respectively,
pulling from the data frame.
Note that we've added a new argument
here called picker and set it to 5.
This informs the Matplotlib backend that
the mouse doesn't have to click directly
on a rendered object that can
be up to 5 pixels away and
it should find the closest object.
What works for you depends on how
you're rendering your charts.
With axis labeled, let's go render this.
Okay, nothing special with this chart yet
but let's wired it up.
We'll create a function called onpick,
which takes on an event.
This event is a pick event which has
different data than the most event.
In particular,
it's got an index value which happens to
correspond to our index and the dataframe.
Now Matplotlib isn't aware
of the data frame but
it renders the data in the same order.
So we can use the data frame iloc indexer
to pull out the origin information.
Now you can see that when
you click on an item,
it renders the origin as we would expect.
And there we have it,
a fairly straight forward example of
adding interactivity to your graphs and
plots.
Now I'll be honest, this looks
like very little code to write and
this lecture was pretty short but there is
a lot of hunting through documentation and
forms that you have to do it in order to
understand the details of the events which
are being passed around.
Pythons lack of static typing has
an unfortunate side effect and
it matches the documentation for
features like events is buried or missing.