This module's assignment is
meant to be unique to you and
will allow you to show off your work
in a portfolio should you want to.
You can make the assignment
challenging and insightful and try and
solve a real world problem.
Or you can make it into
a surface level and
demonstrate the techniques that
you've learned in this course.
The choice is up to you.
When you login to the assignment for
Jupiter notebook,
you'll be given a customized question.
This question will give you a region
in the world, as well as a topic.
We try and generate the region at a city
level, but you're welcome to use data
at the state or provincial level, as well,
or at a countrywide level, as well.
As long as it could encompass
the region that you're actually given.
The topic will be chosen from a list of
things that I am interested in seeing,
sports and athletics, or political events,
or weather and environmental topics.
And we might add more topics over time.
After this, you'll be asked to find at
least two datasets available on the Web
and use them to answer
a question of your choosing.
Now, my motivation for
this assignment is pretty simple.
I want to learn more about the world and
I want you to help teach me through
good information visualizations.
I want you to start to apply your skills
to real world data and gain experience
starting with an ill-defined problem and
moving through the data collection and
cleaning in pandas,
to data representation in that you live.
Finally, I would love to share some of
the great looking visualizations from this
course with others.
If you do not mind we sharing
your solutions, just indicate so
when you upload to the peer review system.
I am looking forward to
seeing what you built.